{
    "questions": [
        {
            "Question": "Presently Daulatabad where Muhammad-bin-Tughlaq had transferred the capital from Delhi is situated near",
            "optionA": "  Mysore ",
            "optionB": "  Nizamabad ",
            "optionC": "  Aurangabad ",
            "optionD": "  Bhopal ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1327, Tughluq passed an order to shift the capital from Delhi to Daulatabad (in present-day Aurangabad, Maharashtra) in the Deccan region of India. ",
            "keyString": "366173s26m41h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which emperor shifted his capital from Delhi to Daulatabad?",
            "optionA": "  Aurangzeb ",
            "optionB": "  Muhammad Bin Tughlaq ",
            "optionC": "  Sher Shah Suri ",
            "optionD": "  Genghis Khan ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMuhammad-bin-Tughlaq transferred his capital from Delhi to Devagiri (Daulatabad) near Aurangabad Maharastra. ",
            "keyString": "366251s26m41h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ibn Batuta visited India during the reign of",
            "optionA": "  Iltutmish ",
            "optionB": "  Alauddin Khalji ",
            "optionC": "  Muhammad bin Tughlaq ",
            "optionD": "  Balban ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tlbn Batuta was a famous Moroccan traveller he visited India during the reign of Sultan Muhammad Bin Tughlaq. ",
            "keyString": "366276s26m41h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the Delhi Sultan to impose Jiziya on Brahmans?",
            "optionA": "  Alauddin Khalji ",
            "optionB": "  Firoz Tughlaq ",
            "optionC": "  Muhammad-bin-Tughlaq ",
            "optionD": "  Balban ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the late 14th century, mentions the memoir of Tughlaq dynasty's Sultan Firoz Shah Tughlaq, his predecessor taxed all Hindus but had exempted all Hindu Brahmins from jizya. Jizya or jizyah is a per capita yearly tax historically levied on non-Muslim subjects, called the dhimma, permanently residing in Muslim lands governed by Islamic law.",
            "keyString": "366294s26m41h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Assertion (A): The nobility under Muhammad bin Tughlaq was a highly homogeneous one.\nReason (R): Royal intervention in the iqta system was as its peak under Muhammad Tughlaq.",
            "optionA": "  Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A ",
            "optionB": "  Both A and R are true but R is not a correct explanation of A ",
            "optionC": "  A is true but R is false ",
            "optionD": "  A is false but R is true ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe tendency towards royal intervention in the iqta system was as its peak under Muhammad Tughlaq. In several cases he handed over the collection of the revenues of the iqtas to either revenue farmers or his own financial officers, the commanders or amirs posted in the iqtas, presumably drawing their pay in cash from the local treasury and having nothing to do directly with revenue collection. ",
            "keyString": "366313s26m41h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Assertion (A): Firuz Shah Tughlaq did not leavy jizya tax.\nReason (R): His influential minister Khan-i-Jahan Maqbul was a converted Hindu.",
            "optionA": "  Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A ",
            "optionB": "  Both A and R are true but R is not a correct explanation of A ",
            "optionC": "  A is true but R is false ",
            "optionD": "  A is false but R is true ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMalik Maqbul or Khan-i-Jahan Maqbul was the Wazir or Prime Minister of the Delhi Sultanate, in the government of Feroz Shah Tughlaq. Yugandhar was converted to Islam and given the name Malik Maqbul. ",
            "keyString": "410908s26m41h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Assertion (A): Sultan Muhammad bin Tughlaq issued currency of copper coins and declared them as legal tender. Reason (R): Sultan's treasury was empty because of his short-sighted projects.",
            "optionA": "  Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A ",
            "optionB": "  Both A and R are true but R is not a correct explanation of A ",
            "optionC": "  A is true but R is false ",
            "optionD": "  A is false but R is true ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMuhammad bin Tughlaq issued token currency; that is coins of brass and copper were minted whose value was equal to that of gold and silver coins. Historian Ziauddin Barani felt that this step was taken by Tughluq as he wanted to annex all the inhabited areas of the world for which a treasury was required to pay the army. Barani had also written that the sultan's treasury had been exhausted by his action of giving rewards and gifts in gold. This experiment failed, because, as said by Barani, \"the house of every Hindu became a mint\". During his time, most of the Hindu citizens were goldsmiths and hence they knew how to make coins. In the rural areas, officials like the muqaddams paid the revenue in brass and copper coins and also used the same coins to purchase arms and horses. As a result, the value of coins decreased and, as said by Satish Chandra, the coins became \"as worthless as stones\". ",
            "keyString": "410943s26m41h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who issued a token currency in copper coins between AD 1329 and 1330?",
            "optionA": "  Alauddin Khilzi ",
            "optionB": "  Ghiyasuddin Tughlaq ",
            "optionC": "  Muhammad bin Tughlaq ",
            "optionD": "  Feroz Tughlaq ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTughlaq\u2019s silver coin was named Adi.However, it was difficult to maintain the supply of gold and silver coins on a large scale. So, Tughlaq replaced those coins and started the circulation of copper and brass coins as the token currency which had the same value of gold or silver coins in 1330-32 CE. ",
            "keyString": "410960s26m41h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Muhammad BinTughlaq transferred his capital from",
            "optionA": "  Delhi to Warangal ",
            "optionB": "  Delhi to Devagiri ",
            "optionC": "  Delhi to Madurai ",
            "optionD": "  Delhi to Vijayanagar ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMuhammad bin Tughlaq was the second ruler of Tughlaq dynasty who ruled from 1324\u20131351.He shifted the capital from Delhi to Devagiri, because it was difficult for him to control South India from there. When the capital was shifted, he now found it difficult to control the North India and went back to Delhi. This step led to nothing but declared him wise fool king in the history. ",
            "keyString": "410996s26m41h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where did the traveller Ibn Batuta come from?",
            "optionA": "  Morocco ",
            "optionB": "  Persia ",
            "optionC": "  Turkey ",
            "optionD": "  Central Asia ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Ibn Batuta was a Muslim Moroccan traveller. All that is known about Ibn Battuta's life comes from the autobiographical information included in the account of his travels, which records that he was of Berber descent, born into a family of Islamic legal scholars in Tangier, Morocco, on 24 February 1304, during the reign of the Marinid dynasty. ",
            "keyString": "411008s26m41h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Muhammad-bin-Tughlaq was a failure because",
            "optionA": "  He was mad ",
            "optionB": "  He was not a practical states man ",
            "optionC": "  He transferred the capital ",
            "optionD": "  He waged war with China ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMuhammad Bin Tughlaq is known as a \u201cMan of Ideas\u201d and can be said one of the most striking sultan of medieval India. He was a trained intellectual, akeen student of Persian poetry and a philosopher, lover of science and mathematics. He is known for the idea of a Central Capital and experiments with a nominal token Currency. These ideas were all good, but he was in hurry and impatient of the slow adoption of his measures. All those who could not keep pace with his imagination, became victim of his wrath and were punished severely. The result was that Muhammad Bin Tughlaq, as a sultan proved himself a complete failure before the history of forces toppled him. ",
            "keyString": "435061s26m41h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who among the following Sultans of Delhi has been described by the historians as the 'mixture of opposites'?",
            "optionA": "  Balban ",
            "optionB": "  Alauddin Khalji ",
            "optionC": "  Muhammad Bin Tughlaq ",
            "optionD": "  Ibrahim Lodi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHistorians have used various epithets while estimating Muhammad Tughlaq. Barani and Ibn-Batuta, his contemporaries found him a \u2018complex person\u2019, a \u2018mixture of opposites.\u2019 He had virtues and vices of extreme intensity. While he was generous, humble and kind, He was very narrow- minded, stubborn and most cruel. He gave gifts to all those whom he liked, he put to death who opposed him. ",
            "keyString": "481394s26m41h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Muhammad-bin-Tughlaq was proficient in",
            "optionA": "  Art ",
            "optionB": "  Music ",
            "optionC": "  Calligraphy ",
            "optionD": "  Philosophy ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMuhammad-bin-Tughlaq was the Turkish Sultan of Delhi. He was known as a 'MAN of knowledge' as he had a great interest in different subjects like, philosphy, mathematics, religion and poetry. ",
            "keyString": "481424s26m41h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Sultans of Tughlaq dynasty issued copper coins instead of silver ones?",
            "optionA": "  Ghiyasuddin Tughlaq ",
            "optionB": "  Muhammad Bin Tughlaq ",
            "optionC": "  Firoz Shah Tughlaq ",
            "optionD": "  Mahmud Tughlaq ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTughlaq\u2019s silver coin was named Adi.However, it was difficult to maintain the supply of gold and silver coins on a large scale. So, Tughlaq replaced those coins and started the circulation of copper and brass coins as the token currency which had the same value of gold or silver coins in 1330-32 CE. ",
            "keyString": "481438s26m41h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Sultan of Delhi established an employment bureau, a charity bureau and a charitable hospital?",
            "optionA": "  Firoz Tughlaq ",
            "optionB": "  Mohammad Tughlaq ",
            "optionC": "  Alauddin Khalji ",
            "optionD": "  Balban ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFiroz Shah Tughlaq established an employment bureau, a charity bureau and a charitable hospital. ",
            "keyString": "481450s26m41h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Arrange the following Tughlaqs in the chronological sequence: \nI. Firuz Tughlaq\nII. Ghiyasuddin Tughlaq\nIII. Abu Bakr\nIV. Nasiruddin Mahmud\nV. Muhammad bin Tughlaq",
            "optionA": "  II,V,I,III,IV ",
            "optionB": "  I,II,V,IV,III ",
            "optionC": "  II,V,I,IV,III ",
            "optionD": "  IV,II,I,V,III ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTughlaqs in the chronological sequence: Ghiyasuddin Tughlaq, Muhammad bin Tughlaq, Firuz Tughlaq, Abu Bakr, Nasiruddin Mahmud. Ghiyath al-Din Tughlaq, Ghiyasuddin Tughlaq, or Ghazi Malik, was the founder of the Tughlaq dynasty in India, who reigned over the Sultanate of Delhi from 1320 to 1325. Muhammad bin Tughlaq was the Sultan of Delhi from 1325 to 1351. He was the eldest son of Ghiyasuddin Tughlaq, the Turko-Indian founder of the Tughlaq dynasty. Sultan Firuz Shah Tughlaq was a Turkic Muslim ruler of the Tughlaq Dynasty, who reigned over the Sultanate of Delhi from 1351 to 1388. Abu Bakr a\u1e63-\u1e62iddiq Abdallah bin Abi Qu\u1e25afah (c. 573 CE - 23 August 634 CE), popularly known as Abu Bakr, was a companion and through his daughter Aisha a father-in-law of the Islamic prophet Muhammad. Nasir ud din Mahmud, Nasir ud din Firuz Shah (reigned: 1246 - 1266) was the eighth sultan of the Mamluk Sultanate (Slave dynasty). ",
            "keyString": "481462s26m41h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        }
    ]
}